software engineering radio episode 63 a
pattern language for distributed systems
welcome everybody to new episode of
software engineering radio in this
episode we are going to talk with Heflin
Haney and Frank Bushman about basically
about mostly about poza for the new
volume in the poster series we'll see
later what it contains before we
actually get started I would just
briefly like to thank the organizers of
the Opie conference port for providing
us this room here which is really nicely
quiet so thanks to six datacom comment
was converted for giving us this this
room here so before we get started with
the content I think you both should
introduce yourself so people know who
you are so who wants to start
yeah I'm Frank Bushman I'm working for
Siemens corporate technology working on
software architecture there specifically
on distributed systems and one of my key
areas of expertise is patents and patent
languages
I'm Kevin honey I'm an independent
consultant I'm based in the UK
my company is curb relay which stands
for curly braket languages okay which
covers a multitude of sins including my
areas of interest and expertise which
programming languages development
process software architecture with a
particular view to talking about
patterns and all levels okay so um
people might have read that somewhere
that poster four and five are have come
out or it actually depends on when we're
going to broadcast this episode so um
can you give us a brief overview of what
poster four and five contain and why you
wrote this book what's the goal
positive for is it covers a broad area
its presents a pattern language for
distributed computing the goal here is
really to give architects and developers
an overview of the were the language of
design behind modern large-scale
distributed systems the work in essence
brings together
pretty much the previous ten years of
poser work in poser one the beginning
started off with key considerations such
as broker and since then many people
including yourself of refine and
expanded on that work both to gave us a
much stronger vocabulary for dealing
with the middleware infrastructure and
with a focus on concurrency and
networking poser 3 gave us a focus on
resource management in each one of these
offers different aspects poser 4 tries
to bring this in the work of others
whether it be the Gang of Four whether
it's Martin Fowler's patterns for
enterprise application architecture and
numerous other works tries to bring them
together with a total of 114 patterns
connected to give us a language for
talking about the architecture of
distributed computing systems not just
distributed object computing but they're
pretty much all modern forms of
demonstrated and practical distributed
systems so it's a mostly a collection of
existing patterns wrapped in a nice
language and supplied with examples and
this kind of stuff that's correct yeah
we took the view that there is a great
deal of literature that goes into detail
so for example impose a to each of the
patterns typically hits 20 to 30 pay s
provides you as detail on everything
provides you with code level examples
and so it provides you with the detail
when you care and when you need it yeah
right and so yeah that this is good if
you if you are when you need that focus
it's good to have it but sometimes you
need to zoom zoom out and get the big
picture and the big picture cannot be
provided in this form it's just going to
be difficult for people so what you'll
find in poser for is that the patterns
we have focused them down to two or
three pages apiece so it's an order of
magnitude less we have taken that we
have focused them with respect to
distributed computing so many patterns
in read documents in these patterns has
been a great challenge to connect them
together it's not just a rewriting it's
not just a writer yeah it's a refocusing
so therefore the generality of some
patterns what you'll find is that some
of the general cases where they apply
are actually omitted for the simple
reason we say okay this is about this
pattern in the
texture distributed computing it is not
about solving certain other kinds of
problem we recognized that we provide
full set of references but we are
focused on this one goal which helps us
to keep the pattern length sort of short
but they're not sort of superficial
abstracts that actually goes quite some
depth we bind it together
with an overview of each of the
categories of patterns we have a number
of categories that we've formed for them
built toggle bar these and we preview
this with discussion of the concepts
behind the patterns the patent language
and obviously distributed systems binded
together with a narrative example that
draws on a good majority of the patterns
and shows them in practice so that
people can actually see how we thread
through and create a sequence of it and
then follow the patterns themselves okay
Frank those are five yeah poser five was
actually intended to be another part of
poser for was one big book the
originally poser for an opposer five was
supposed to be a single volume in the
post a serious but our peer reviewers
about a year ago strongly suggested to
think about splitting it into two
volumes am just for dressing their
target audience much much better and to
make sure it's not 900 pages right so in
total poser four and poser five are
about nine that's why I say and besides
get to have them split it into two
volumes poser five is about conceptual
foundations of patterns since the early
days 1992 to 1994 and a little later
with copes white book on software
patterns little material little art only
few articles were published about the
concept of patterns much of what is in
the heads of developers and people about
patterns is actually conceptual work
from the early days of the community
however now we know much more about
Hanz time didn't stand still yeah
mm and we have 2007 now so the goal of
posa 5 is to revisit the early
conceptual work discuss it with the
hindsight of today extended and adjusted
according to what we know now and also
to complete it with other conceptual
knowledge that we learned and collected
over the years so it started out by
revisiting the concept of a standalone
pattern based on the Gang of Four and
pose our one work and others and then
develops further concept like
complementary patterns where multiple
patterns
address the same general problem
according to different forces and they
provide different solutions so our
solution space is broader we are
visiting the concept of pattern
complements where a specific set of
patterns recurs over and over again in a
very specific arrangement to resolve a
larger problem that cannot be addressed
by a single pattern alone we then go
into patterns stories well we discuss
how a narrative form of a bunch of
patterns helped or informs the design of
a specific system and then go into
pattern sequences which is a concept
that was let's say it is quite old it
was introduced by Christopher Alexander
but the pattern community actually
didn't pay much attention to it until
recently so we explore pattern sequences
which abstract the story from the story
so it's the naked order of the patterns
and that gives you some advice and then
go into pattern languages another topic
of the book is that we address a pet on
collections various forms of organizing
patterns from catalogs to languages and
we also discussed different views on
patterns such as the semiotics view
introduced by James No
four years ago or a problem frame view
which was quite new until we addressed
it now there are some other folks also
investigating on this concept on this
view so it's more conceptual overview
it's a conceptual closed erection
closure actually if the rows are serious
so is it is it fair to say that those
are four is probably more intended for
the practitioner and puts a five more
for the parents community or maybe you
know the philosopher or is it yes and
now from the one perspective yes but
from the other perspective specifically
with respect to patent sequences
complementary patterns and also better
languages as a whole of method or
methodological advice there how to use a
language okay what is the process
embedded there what can I expect from a
language from what can I expect from a
sequence and what where doesn't it help
me another difference between the two
books is they are they are close in the
sense they were originally going to be
one volume and if you like parts of four
was originally intended to be a worked
example of the principles and ideas that
we had worked very we always kept an eye
on the practice and so when we separated
the two parts
it was the principles are still there
but we've had to only discuss them
briefly but as if five allows people to
really understand a lot more of the
thinking and the history behind it so in
extracting what became a very large
worked example yeah comparable in length
to poser to we elaborated and expanded
what is now pose of five with a number
of shorter worked examples and is it's
very proud to be focused it is not
simply a presentation of theory it is
and let's see how this applies we're
very very keen to demonstrate that we
pick as many examples as seems
appropriate at each time we try and
demonstrate through example the relevant
parts for patent the weaknesses or
strengths of particular styles and the
various trade offs the styles of design
that are of interest and we
draw on all of these its although it is
fair to say that certainly if one is
interested in the more philosophical
aspects then those are five will have
been more rewarding pose of five also
offers something for people who would
not consider themselves philosophers of
patterns or even members of the pants
community but where they want to go
beyond they've read maybe two or three
pounds books they'd like to know a
little more about the thinking in the
inner cities behind it but they would
still consider that both their feet
firmly in the world of practice and
polls are five contains real code that's
not just theory okay but one point
though asking what is the valuable
contribution in the audience and in fact
the entire series is worth more than the
sum of its parts because of course those
are one through poser three together
with other pattern books that describe
patterns in in detail in code level
detail they provide the groundwork poza
for connects them from the perspective
of distributed around five provides the
methodology yeah yeah so people may read
pose a foreign and need to use some of
the patterns and they can go back to
puzzle one too and others have a series
and everywhere else
Andy poser five provides them in the
conceptual framework how to use them of
how everything fits together okay
so um in this discussion we however
still want to like focus on on pose our
foreign and look at these patterns for
building distributed systems and we've
done discussions of pattern works before
in the podcast and one I think
successful approach is to really look at
the different sections because this
outlines the process and the different
concerns of building a distributed
system and then picking two or three of
the parents or maybe for whatever of the
patterns in that section and therefore
show like more or less an example
through the through the whole thing so I
think we should get started and the
first chapter in this language section
of the book is called from math to
structure so I guess this
covers the basic architectural styles
yes if you start building an application
whether distributed or not you need to
have an idea of what the system is all
about I mean the fact that it is
distributed is a challenge but
nevertheless you need an ocean and an
understanding what you want to build and
the patterns in the chapter from what to
structure help you to petition the big
bowl of requirements you have into
tangible parts that help you building
your system so it's the first step of
transforming requirement into software
structure these requirements are more
technical requirements and not
necessarily germane or functional
requirement it can be a mixture of both
for instance we start the first pattern
is domain water and that focus is purely
on understanding your domain if you have
no idea of what your system should do
and what the domain is and what your
domain abstractions are what the work
flows in your domain and you well you
can't build a proper system yeah and
then there are other patterns like
layers more of your controller or
microkernel or reflection that address
technical concerns of petitioning or
providing a fundamental baseline
architecture where other patterns like
pipes and filters shared repository or
blackboard address certain style of
computation processing data streams
sequence data so this is more domain
related so it's a mixture of both but
actually it starts from the domain right
and then addresses key technical aspects
and key properties of computation in
that domain with the requirements as is
the case with many systems requirements
tend to come undifferentiated and yes
it's it tends to be very tempting for
somebody who's technically focused to
sort of run off and say right we're
going to build a distributed system
somebody going to find out what people
want actually want to run over
you know what's the domain what we'll do
that second and it is although we may be
very strongly technically focused in a
lot of the detail in the book it has to
be anchored in some understanding of the
problem and we we work from that so
there is a reason it's not just a
historical reason for calling this from
mud to structure echoing equivalent
section imposes one it really is there
is a sense of something to be built and
we want to separate and we want to
provide ourselves importantly with a
partitioning and this is that the coarse
partitioning and sort of style decisions
yeah that we take we want to be able to
give ourselves the opportunity to think
about things separately and that's one
of the key ideas is okay maybe we do not
have the level of understanding of the
domain or the domain may be fluid but
the technology may be mature on the
other hand the technology and our
application of it may be very fluid yeah
and the domain may be understood and so
on we would like the opportunity to keep
these worlds sort of know more
intertwined than necessary but a good
understanding of each they they each
belong somewhere so that is why the the
patent language we we spent some time
arriving at the root pattern being
domain model and that was the most
satisfying and stable thing and when we
reflect on how we actually approached
systems building this also matched our
experience very well yeah and this
domain model model stuff is so if you
talk about references to other work then
this is obviously Eric Evans stuff right
it relates to Eric Evans work it also
relates to Martin Fowler's work and the
idea is that of the stuff of the system
now what is the thing that we are going
to build this for it is not a system
that is concerned with sockets and IP
addresses unless you're actually running
a network management system then that is
of course your domain but there is that
notion if there is some domain there is
a vocabulary there are ideas and there
is there's somebody cares about
something and so within that space we
there are many many ideas we can bring
to bear we can talk about sort of the
domain driven design yeah is technique
we can look back at domain analysis
approaches feature oriented
analysis metamodels yeah we can
differentiate things using feature
modeling and : IOT variability and
errors and so on we're not dictating and
describing one style for partitioning
the domain we are saying that it needs
to be done and there when we've site
appropriate works and then we continue
into the other architectural
considerations yeah a domain model also
then not only refers to the other
patterns that we present in the chapter
and the domain driven design and other
works but this is also an entry point
for us to reference all the domain
specific patterns document and so far
such as martin fowler's follows analysis
patterns after healthcare and corporate
finance and all the telecom patterns
documented throughout the property
serious so it's in its the root pattern
of the language and we referenced the
relevant relevant work to identify the
definable domain model it's a starting
point for our for the pattern length
patterns in our language and also
references all the domain specific
patterns okay so then the next step then
really is technical it's called
distribution infrastructure and and
deals obviously with nuts and bolts of
building a scalable technically sound
distributed system right yes so the
second sect chapter is about the core
patterns that help you to connect
distributed components yeah originally
we started with broker which is much the
remote method invocation style
we got a suggestions from Doug Lee that
this is Kobo style only yeah that is
true so we now have messaging and we
have published subscribe as Co
infrastructures as well speaking of
messaging that is the entry point into
Gregor hobbies and Bobby Wolf's work so
we connect that book as well we don't
repeat each of the patterns in there but
just some of the the messaging which is
root and the key patterns referenced by
messaging right and if you listeners
look back at our interview with Lego
hoping which I just wanted to point out
that not just the the book
is organized in a way that we reference
previous work also the podcast is
organized no way that this interview can
reference previous interview episodes
and we talked about these different
sections in Diego's book and we talked
about these entry patterns to those
separate sections and exactly those
entry patterns are now referenced here
in this like bigger more encompassing
pattern language this is really cool
right so we have messaging message
channel message endpoint message
translate and message also exactly
included in our language described on
two to three pages and in these patterns
we reference the other patterns as they
are referenced in Gregor's book exactly
it really points into his pattern
language and that broadens of course the
scope of the language of the 114
patterns that we describe yeah in talk
by this
transitive references we reach about 300
different patterns this is cool so one
of the other points to pick up on is we
in trying to write this book we wanted
to write a pattern language for
distributed computing not simply a
pattern language for distributed object
RFC start computing that was that was
quite valuable
so in embracing that we are looking at
proven architectures many with different
characteristics but we find that in this
distribution infrastructure chapter we
are looking at the plumbing that the key
plumbing that you're going to see from
the outside and then we decompose from
there and there are many commonalities
the next level down but we also did some
pet and refactoring broker is a good
example broker is originally described
in poser one and it has a very specific
structure over time we learn that this
structure might not be the most
emotional one the most ideal one to
describe the ingredients of broker and
the mounting patterns book was it
actually that disassembled and
reassembled broker and came up with a
new structure and that is also reflected
in our language so wherever we identify
patterns and that need refactoring or
decom
position and reassembly well we did it
so even those patterns that are well
known and well documented or carefully
revisited to address the latest
knowledge in what patterns are document
to watch other patterns they could refer
and broker for instance didn't just
reflect the structure outlined in the
remoting patterns we also introduced
some of the security aspects that are
covered in the security patterns book so
it's even more and we actually have a
discussion on this evolution in poser 5
using broker as an example that from the
days of poser 1 there are four or five
different versions yeah and the latest
and greatest version of course is in
those are four yeah and so inside the
same sense as you're referencing Drago
and bobbies stuff in the same sense you
also reference their moulding pattern
stuff we can we also covered in a
previous episode on the podcast so and
you can go back and look at the details
and we cover security pattern stuff
which might be a future episode
certainly yes and so it's it's on the
list so basically what you're saying is
there are those two different styles
messaging and remote procedure call and
publish subscribe and publish subscribe
how is that different from messaging
it's an even more loose coupling okay so
it's messaging one-to-many more or less
I can dynamically register and with
messaging with messaging you care who
you're talking to
it is very much as in messaging in the
form of SMS you megaphone yeah so the
idea of publish/subscribe II although
they share many features in common yeah
at one level the intent is actually
slightly different I want asynchronous
end-to-end communication with messaging
with publish/subscribe we can actually
have multiple publishers and multiple
subscribers who do not care about each
other's identity it is a very very
different style at that level there are
other quality of service concerns that
come and simply don't fit with messaging
but it didn't cover streaming right
because that could be considered a lot
of for more distributed
systems or how does that fit in we had a
discussion about hopes and we I mean
pipes and filters is about streaming but
it's not about transporting a stream
over distribution network keeping
quality of service and stuff no no it's
not streaming as you discuss it in the
remoting patterns book but we consider
there's a discussion that we had because
pipes and filters is also described in
the messaging patterns by cracker and
Bobbie here and we consider this a pipes
and filters more as a way to organize
applications rather than the fundamental
style of communication and in between
the filters there is a pipe that uses
messaging there's a way to discussion
what are the fundamental style of
communication and we have this remote
method invocation you are dependent on
the point to point to point
communication depending on the
interfaces of the components you invoke
messaging is you have a point-to-point
communication but are independent of
functional interfaces of your of the
component except that you have to agree
on the message structure so well it is
in the message format yes but it's a
looser coupling yeah and eventing or
publish/subscribe is then an even looser
cup and because you not even care for
the identity that were the fundamental
styles yes streaming is an application
of that is an application of that
because if you look into the messaging
patterns they actually discuss message
sequencing to form streams so in some
sense the message pattern that we also
have in our book is an entry point to to
to compose message streams which then
can be used to transmit data streams
with quality of service from filter to
fill through pipes so it is covered but
we don't consider it as a fundamental
style of communication okay
next section is even more detailed or
more technical so after discussing the
general style of remote
communicate and distribution the next
one deals with event D multiplexing and
dispatching this sounds to me an awful
bit like poza - right
curiously enough yes it does the two
dominant patterns in their reactor and
proact you can say and those are those
provide that the routes we are receiving
messages these messages are in this
censuses we refer to these from the
point of view of events handle this
these are coming in from wherever they
need to go somewhere these capture the
different styles and the different
concerns following on from that we have
except a connector and asynchronous
completion token with this aspect we are
now definitely within the middleware as
opposed to within right within the code
we're not out on the network anymore
yeah and so the concerns the chapter is
very is relatively short but very
focused perhaps the greatest challenge
here is as you say this sounds an awful
lot like pose or - and we just said pose
a tube embraces some phenomenal detail
reactor and projector in poser - taking
up a lot of real estate so we discussed
some of that in you in the interview
with Dutch MIT a while ago so again we
can connect to a previous episode so our
challenge here was to represent
faithfully the the intent and offer
people sufficient sufficient detail to
make reasoned decisions about stuff but
without necessarily trying to cover all
the same ground as poser - it yeah
hopefully as I look at the at the table
of content which we use as a kind of
guide through the episode here I can see
that reactor has two stars associated
with it and pro actor has none what are
these stars about and why doesn't pro
actor have stars we have followed the as
it were the the star rating that was
used originally by Christopher Alexander
to sort of rate so degree of confidence
or applicability of a particular patent
we are not making comments on the
quality of the patent itself we are
looking at it specifically in the
context of typical distributed computing
well broadly applicable it's okay
and two stars mean that we have a high
degree of confidence everybody who said
yeah this is something you would
typically want and typically find and
the risks are relatively few in other
words so there are very few dark patches
if we rate something as one star then
that sort of adds a slightly cautionary
note often some of the one star patterns
are in contrast to some of the two star
patterns that are in the language
sometimes they are complimentary yes
this is applicable but there are sort of
more edge cases where this one reply we
also have noticed some know star
patterns as you say is one of them and
in that sense we when we said reactor we
looked at react and we saw bright this
is this is typical this is common this
is easy to understand it is it is very
widespread prior actor is far more
specific it's also more challenging to
implement yes hardly anybody uses it
because hardly anybody understands it
that that goes back to the challenge it
is it is a more complex path yet but
that does not mean it is not applicable
it not used to see applicability so it
is contained in the language right and
some patterns were not included in the
language simply because we either did
not find them appropriate so for example
when maybe maybe later we talk about
object adapters but we don't talk about
class adapters we don't find scope for
that
and I think our favorite pattern that we
emitted is the only pattern that got a
negative star rating when we looked at
it as a single which is of course yeah
everybody knew there so it's a hundred
and fourteen not a hundred and fifteen
okay okay
after those technical infrastructure
details of handling Network events and
stuff we now get one level up towards
how to partition an application more
specifically about how to partition
interfaces and this is actually a
relatively long topic chapter sorry
which which means that there is quite a
bit to say about how to design
interfaces which many people would
probably say oh what's the problem there
yeah it's actually quite long chapter
and for good reasons because interface
design designing interfaces specifically
for components in a distributed system
is a challenge and
we were surprised when we started out to
lay out the language that we have a hole
here a white space in the language and
we it took us a month to discover it's
all about interfaces and we also
discovered that only few parents were
actually described it was somehow
implicitly there in the community but
not explicitly documented can you maybe
outline some of the challenges you have
and desired if it's designing interfaces
especially maybe the you know the
problem between the forces that tend to
make the interface is good for from a
functional purpose and the forces that
drive you towards a way that makes the
system scale better and then maybe take
some of the patterns in this chapter to
outline how they solve these forces is
contradicting forces yeah first of all
you need to separate interface from
implementation yeah obviously yeah
otherwise you can get access to an
interface in a remote address space so
we address that as the fundamental that
unexplained to face how to do this
because this is said quickly but doing
it properly is difficult other patterns
then address the scope of interfaces
having to narrow interfaces won't help
much of the client if you have too broad
interfaces you get a shopping lists of
methods and we actually don't use and if
one of them signatures changes are you
affected your code breaks you don't want
this so we have the notion of
role-specific interfaces which is
expressed in the extension interface
pattern then in large distributed
systems you might want to know more
about a component then can then the
typical interfaces offer and we offer
introspection and some clients like test
frameworks have no clue about the
interfaces you saw you need a dynamic
access so that is our scripting right
and then we have lots of patterns that
help you hiding infrastructure details
because clients are not interested in
all this component is
on the other side of the network or
there might be load balancing or any
quality service involved I just want to
use a method or a function and so we
have patents addressing that
so proxy business delegated facade are
not necessarily about how the interface
looks but rather about how to decouple
the interface from the implementation
and separated from technical concerns
that networking network failure
management availability concerns load
balancing and stuff behind the business
delegate for instance a lot of things
can happen there are security proxies
which hide some security stuff so the
technical concern these patterns like
proxy business delegating facade help
you separating structural and technical
concerns of the component implementation
right and batch method is obviously a
way of improving performance if you have
instead of you know calling an operation
15 times you call it once and get all
the data or work said about that's
correct yeah one of the goals in the
interface partitioning chapter and one
of the reasons it precedes some of the
other chapters that are more
implementation focused is that although
we often talk about interfaces it's a
common oversight developers tend to
think first in terms of implementation
and structure and second in terms of
interfaces and often when they come to
do so the interfaces aren't driven by
that there's a number of systems that
have suffered from a sort of a naive
approach whether it's not understanding
how systems may evolve over time or
whether it is just assuming that the
techniques they learnt for their local
sequential style of programming Wilson
will scale sufficiently and quite
frankly some of these are just too fine
grained the idea that we can have a pure
interface and not worry about the
context of deployment in the context in
which that interface is going to be used
the idea that this is an implementation
issue it's it's an optimization issue
and share not affect the interface
that's a it's a pleasant little fantasy
that some people are trying to live out
and the number of methods of also trying
to pursue but in reality this is not a
question of optimization this is
actually a question of making the thing
work batch method is is the practical
way of considering this and from that
point of view one of the actual opening
actors stresses the importance of
context with respect to design and what
they want to do with a solution you know
if you're using a simple iterator in one
environment it's a solution that works
in that context it's sequential it's
happy it's good we're all pleased it
just doesn't work as straightforward
iterator just doesn't scale to a
distributed system you have to think a
bit harder and it's not only it's not a
matter of optimization this is a matter
of architecture yeah but you do it
because you want to make sure some
technical concern or yeah this is you
can't optimize afterwards but it's it's
it's a kind of its kind of optimization
or it's a consideration that will affect
the very presentation of the interfaces
it's not something that lives inside the
private sector right so in this case
technical and functional concerns are
not orthogonal that's yeah they they
interact with one another and that is
that is part of the challenge indeed
it's part of the challenge of trying to
come up with the chapter categories but
yes that is the you know that they some
of those some of the patents moved
around a little bit during right to here
as we sort of said well this this
pattern has two aspects you can appear
here or it can here appear there
ultimately we felt that dealing with
given that most systems present multiple
objects and there are very few systems
that don't have multiple things of
interest then access to these objects
and therefore things like iteration and
how we gain access to aggregate content
matter at the interface level therefore
we promoted it to that okay so after
discussing the interface level it's
obviously the next step to look at
component partitioning and how the
implementation can be broken down right
yeah this is the chapter on component
partitioning within this we take a
broad-brush view we're not teaching
people how to do our design that's not
the goal we're making a very component
centric view we the counterpart to our
explicit interface is the absolute
implementation it's the idea that these
two creatures are not two sides of the
same coin not just two sides of the same
coin they can actually be even more
loosely coupled they tell a different
story they feel and drive one another
and again it was part of this conscious
decision to keep them in separate
chapters so that they each fell they
each have their strong focus and within
that we start partitioning and saying
okay it's no good to just have a slab of
stuff Campos whole part we talked about
bringing some of the other classic
patterns such as compensator yeah and
then there and we talked about other
concerns that are actually much coarser
than the traditional object a
consideration master/slave half object
plus protocol and replicate a component
group for dealing with implementation at
the broader level again still behind a
stable interface yeah master/slave half
object less protocol and replicated
component group actually address aspects
of distribution and the quality of
service like performance scalability
availability fault tolerance so this is
people will probably know what
master/slave is about and what
replications good for but what does half
objectors protocol half object post
protocol is addressing the fact that if
you have only a single component
implementation deployed to one specific
place you might run into performance
problems because if you just access the
functionality through a proxy the calls
always go over the network and if you
now consider a telephone call and I'm
sitting here in Munich and my the other
party is sitting in let's say Hong Kong
where is the call object is it in
between well where to put it if I have
it in some place and the parties access
the object through proxies we run into
performance problems then the idea is
that functionality should be as close to
the address space where it is used and
if certain functionality is only in the
used in one address space for what some
clients it should be there because it
can be executed locally I would really
want attach the object it is one half
and the network is not used at all like
giving me the dial tone doesn't need the
other party yes
likewise ringing the other party's phone
doesn't need me as a caller so
on the other side of the half that can
be actually more than two half second
arrangement there is functionality
implemented that is executed locally in
the other address space that can be
overlaps but the idea is in each clients
address space implement those
functionality that can be executed
locally there and a protocol a kind of
peer-to-peer protocol connects the
different half so that they know one
another and form a centralized unit here
and whenever I control flow requires
components in multiple address spaces to
cooperate the network is used or if
state needs to be aligned paradox is
each Network call gets more expensive
but the overall performance in the loop
hood is maximized your the more you can
execute locally the less you use the
network and that is the a common
technique for improving performance in
network systems and also if you smoke of
roxies right
and also if you think of a conference
call if you have a central
implementation in a call if it fails the
conference is gone if you have a half
object's protocol implementation and one
half fails only one part is what we all
know that people trust doesn't only
address performance and also other
qualities like for tolerance or even
scalability because with each new party
each in your address space you have
another half object so we address these
concerns that deal with distribution and
deployment of functionality in that
chapter just sort of bring that back to
the other key point where we started is
that whilst all of this is going on we
are maintaining the illusion each each
client believes it has the object that
is that the key point this is why this
lives in component partitioning after
this was not component partitioning
separating components and their
interactions some extent we now look at
application control which probably
structures the diff
rolls in an application more
specifically so what wants to give it a
shot
application control is actually about we
have model-view-controller
yeah somewhere else I think somewhere
else another chapter but how do we
control the model so he said you have
controllers and the model yeah how do
you do this and actually Martin Fowler
in his patterns of enterprise
application he had a whole lot of
patterns like page controller front
controller application controller
different types of views like template
view insurance from you impose a 1s
command processor that deals with
scheduling so in this chapter we
actually collect and describe the key
patterns that help you realizing useful
controllers and useful views in terms of
presentation and control of application
functionality and that was decorated
that is decorated with some of the
security patterns like authorization and
firewall proxies that play a significant
role in distributed applications so it
is more or less a summary of the key
patterns in martin fowler's book and
some of the relevant patterns in the
security patterns book that helps you to
access the functionality of your
application from a remote user interface
or remote address so for example just to
give a little bit of a flavor what's in
there we'd have the page control of the
way which appendages probably webpages
or something not only web pages but
could code so a form-based
oh yeah okay so it's but we are in this
case we generalize Martin's web based
focus a little because if you have a
form based interview interface that also
models a workflow right so it's not just
it is not limited to web the one of and
one of the other aspects and looking at
this generalization we're aware that in
fact if we have it in our example they
worked example the warehouse story we
can't assume that people are just
sitting there looking at app pcs looking
at web interfaces across the web this is
a very large and important class of
distributed systems but it's certainly
not the only one yeah hopefully various
devices
so in looking at form control we might
be driving this from mobile devices so
their point is we are trying to be we're
trying to capture the essence of a very
large class or larger class of
distributor systems than just merely web
or just classic object RPC yeah you
mentioned the workflow yeah a workflow
this is somewhat in application
controller somewhat but it's not
explicitly you don't have no style we
don't claim that our language is
complete okay so everybody is invited to
connect other patterns into the language
that is actually one of the original
intentions that we also had that that
passed the book around asked the book
around and you can add more chapters or
new parents to chapters you can refactor
the existing patterns and so that they
include more reference or different
references or different references and
definitely the area of workflow based
systems or business rule roses yeah is
not yet covered in the depth that might
might be really appropriate or useful
but if we wouldn't may if we don't make
a cut somewhere
it's whatever finish and the idea was to
this is the finish at some point
consider this as a first release an
application controller is probably one
way into workflow driven control flow
mm-hmm but it's not the only one and
this is an area that may be addressed in
a subsequent version is there any
concrete plans yet to pass it around any
volunteers yet was a tear we're gonna
add another two pages you know I didn't
ask it for that reason
yeah we don't we don't have concrete
plans at this point for doing that and
you'll find that we have obviously have
to have an emphasis we all there we try
to be even-handed and neutral on a
number of topics as you say the workflow
if you look in application controller is
one way in we have state models handled
elsewhere within the language these
things can there are many elements
within the language that can be combined
and of course should readers find that
they need to deal with a domain or style
that is not covered there and pose a
five will give them the ingredients
setter
warehouse yeah okay next one is again
looks a bit like pose our to concurrency
stuff it is so it includes the for
concurrency patterns that we have in in
poser 2 which is half some kvass only
the followers active object and wanted
to object and it's like we already
discussed for the event handling
patterns we are compressing them showing
the key conceptual aspects around then
the details of the implementation and
leave it by that okay and then we go to
a synchronization which is obviously
related to concurrency and of course yes
it's it represents potentially the other
side in doing so we have stuck fairly
close to the sort of conventional
improvement area of synchronizing state
change so you don't talk about
transactional memory and not talk about
transactional memory we init we mention
we talked briefly about lock free
programming but we point out this is
very hard and there are a lot of things
in terms of memory models that are still
maturing out right but in as much as we
are looking at stuff that is lock free
we do highlight a couple of techniques
that relate to that we include double
check locking although just to make
people feel good about this it has no
star rating we include copied value why
synchronize when you can copy we include
a copy on a ride know if this is
actually just I give you a copy oh okay
it is a snapshot and this the notion
here is if I deal with copies of data
then clearly there is no scope for
synchronization no need for it we are
synchronizing state change the Phillip
side of that is immutable value if there
is no state change there is no need for
synchronization we've been discussing
these things in our various concurrency
episodes and also in the interview with
Brian gets and David Holmes so I think
we can maybe skip the rest of this
chapter and don't discuss it much - yeah
and the rest of the chapter is it's very
much on the locking side of things and
people will be familiar with pans from
yes yeah and from poser - yeah object
interaction the next chapter yes it is
you have to answer yes it is so what
we're looking at here is
the interaction the dialogue between
objects the oral components for that
matter or is it really okay today we are
focusing on the object here these are
the ocean opponents yeah we're actually
looking very much not at the deployment
view of things we are actually looking
at the interaction between the runtime
objects so component objects to
differentiate from components so we are
now getting slowly but certainly into
the realm of design patterns golf stuff
the traditional design patents indeed we
kick off with observer because a classic
interaction one yeah and of course in
this work a careful careful
study will reveal the fact that we have
differentiated observer from polishers
subscriber which is one its
architectural the other is design on a
it's not so much that it's the it's the
level at which they or other the
significance of the decision in that
case the locality we are actually seeing
the publish/subscribe is broadly across
the network and will involve
distribution infrastructure whereas
observer is a much more local yes and
local approach that that's what I meant
about a designer we spent a bit of time
imposer 5 really talking about these
terms architects are a bit more detail
but that's not that's not the focus of
pose of 4 so right we we look at things
like that we include observer double
dispatch and mediator command yes many
of these are familiar from the Gang of
Four memento importantly context object
what's that context object makes its way
in here because the idea is that it
expresses an execution context
traditionally people have sort of leant
towards using some kind of global or
magic access and they've been very very
clever so clever that some systems have
suffered the problems of this we're
talking Singleton's and akin and people
end up trying to solve the solution and
working around this the notion of a
context object is that from a component
point of view I really do want to
isolate my component from external
assumptions I want to do this for
reasons currency of reading students of
security for reasons of testability if I
pass you the execution context I either
component infrastructure I'm telling you
what to expect I can control that
can work to it you have a simpler life
everybody's happy this is the focus of
context object as a pattern it's
actually been around for a very long
time the earliest I've been able to find
is the scheme the scheme eval function
and it actually appears in the Gang of
Four book hiding in the interpreter
pattern we talk a little bit more about
this in pair to five but as a documented
pattern it's very recent it history
really only goes back in the last four
years yeah this is one of these patterns
that has been documented and redock you
mented a number of times in a relatively
short space of time okay the next one is
again on design and implementation level
level and it's about adaptation and
extension yes so this chapter is more or
less about the classic Gang of Four
patterns that deal with adaptation
extension flexibility so we have bridged
their chain of responsibility
interpreter visitor decorator template
method strategy and we extended this
chapter with a couple of other patterns
documented here and they are like like
repres art and all object executes
around objects so and so on but
nevertheless um one specific pattern
that we like could discuss here is
object adapter rather than having the
classic adapter pattern or the gang of
four we just focused on object adapter
if you read the Gang of Four adapter pet
experience two patterns object adapter
and class adapter and so we had a
discussion of whether or not so include
both or in case we just include one
which one and we thought that in terms
of how we think adaptation in
distributed systems could work is it's
more the object adapter you delegate
something to another object rather than
using inheritance to connect the
difference you know that can introduce
the fragile base class problem and
inheritance or knowledge anomalies which
are specifically annoying in distributed
systems so you avoid this and that is
why object adapter is included rather
than class adapter and we discussed this
issue in poser 5 you
see those are four and pulse' five are
connected terms of a couple of things
that are just implicitly visible in
poser four and here our strategy in the
podcast breaks down a little bit because
at the time we broadcast this one we
probably won't have had an episode
specifically on the golf design patterns
but we are promised I mean we expect
everybody knows them anyway but we'll
still we still promise that we'll do
that at some point okay anything else on
this chapter there are a couple of other
contrasts we've talked about object
adapter and class adapter and in this
particular case class adapter didn't
make it into the book but there there
are a couple of others there's a playoff
between strategy and template method for
example we gave strategy two stars and
template method one star we find that
the loser coupling delegation style with
strategy is stronger yeah but we also
find template method has has its place
with the more convenient if some it has
certain convenience so we we acknowledge
the difference there likewise we
included interceptor and decorator which
are sometimes used to solve similar
problems but interceptor is much less
intrusive it offers an orthogonal
approach to instrumentation basically
ALP yeah yeah it allows you to put extra
functional features in whilst keeping
the kind of route interface statement
but the additional functionality is
independent of the specific interface
precisely yeah and and decorator
although it's kind of a classic it's
it's as in some ways it is not it was
always a favorite teaching example but
in project in practice people tend not
to use it to be quite frank there are
many subtleties to it and object that
entity for object identity being a
classic one and some methods should not
should or should not be propagated
termination being a guy being a classic
example and then if you have to worry
about memory management there further
Pro yeah so it still has its role in
terms of you know literally decoration
but we felt this was this was fairly low
so it got no stars there whereas we gave
interceptor two stars has a very strong
proven track record in component and
distributed computing
behavior the next stuff yeah this is a
short little chapter we looked at we
looked at the space it's a concern that
again another aspect we spend a little
more time talking about in pose of 5
that it's a concern that in the Gang of
Four book there is one pattern that is
related to mobile behavior and it is
known as the state pattern we're just
not use much or is it well that's the
thing it's not used by some people
because of its inherent complexity but
it is overused by others because of its
name in the end so this is a state
pattern or it's the state pattern before
we go we have a state diagram here we're
going to solve the problem that way and
it is certainly applicable we favor
using it's also known as named objects
for States and we also recognize there
are other complementary patterns that
fit this space methods for states with
methods for States the idea is that we
don't so much delegate to a whole object
we don't end up with a larger separate
class hierarchy all the behavior
actually lives in the object of interest
instead what we have is if we use C++
specific terminology for a moment in the
sense of using pointers what we have
there is each state is represented its
behavior is represented by effectively
nothing more than a struct that has
pointers to the right methods for that
state so all the behaviors not scattered
across objects we've merely it created
if you like a dynamic vtable approach
and that is you can't do in Java so
which you can't it yes this this is
actually one of the one of the key
things is when when this pattern was
originally documented the Shepherd
proposed that I should present a Java
example and I said but Java is not the
right language to do this in there are a
number of problems but usually don't
have a method pointlessly yeah exactly I
said because Java is not an
object-oriented language in spite of
rumor to the contrary oh that's a
separate episode into there's no and so
it's a very context-specific one so we
find this is relevant in languages like
C++ we find is relevant in languages
like C sharp and dynamically typed
languages it is immediately relevant
addala and
presume you have an episode
that um yep not yet a different one so
methods for states in that sense offers
a more appropriate one and again this
brings back the context specificity of
design and we wrap up the chapter with
collections for States which deals about
collectively treating objects and
similar States but X in this in a
separate context yeah it's an extrinsic
state model right there's an expensive
one yeah good distinction
next one resource management Frank yeah
resource management is actually the
largest chapter in the entire book
righteous not only for the reason that
there's a entire poseur volume poser 3
which we have also already talked about
on the podcast but we discovered in then
III wondered why this is the biggest
chapter it has more patterns in it than
there are in pose delivery here I see
container from server ID it's also a
resource management pattern components
also resources are need to be managed
and we discovered that resource
management is a key issue in building
yeah usable distributed systems that
resources are limited even in a
distributed system and therefore things
like containers like how to find
components look up how to configure
components how to manage resources how
to create components how to delete them
and things like that are of significant
importance so so it addresses all the
resource management and lifecycle and
lifetime patterns that we know it's even
containing some of the Gang of Four
patterns like abstract Factory and Billy
also the way to really resource yeah so
there is somewhat that it's somewhat no
surprise that this chapter is the
largest was at the bottom of the system
you deal with the resources and resource
management is everything in a
distributed system it is interesting
that when we actually tried to divide
the define up this chapter in different
ways we found that the coupling between
the parts was far too strong then
eventually we settled for very careful
ordering a very careful sequence of
disclosure within the
chapter which benefits the reader as
well as the authors and in terms of
dealing with all these issues so um just
to connect there are things like Blasi
acquisition resource pooling effect
Viktor activator so these are all
different ways of handling not just the
creation of resources but specifically
also their deletion which is arguably
the the bigger challenge in practice and
not just the deletion the entire
lifecycle activator is somewhat in
between so we start from the creation
and then have different intermediate
states such as resource cache for
instance you don't delete the object if
they're awhile and if they re accessed
then they are returned to some client so
it's the entire lifecycle that we
address or leasing is also more about
lifecycle then about pure deletion right
except somebody acquires a resource and
releases it and then what happens yeah
yeah so it's more than just object life
time in this life cycle right uh-huh
which explains one of the reasons why we
did find it very difficult to separate
this because the activation reactivation
acquisition and so on all of these
concerns ultimately grow from the fact
that in the past people are focused on
creational patterns which is a nice
starting point
the minute you start hitting large-scale
systems and distributing them the
creation is only it is just just one
hand and the sound of one hand clapping
is really not very much unless you hit
somebody and that's that's really the
reason that the chapter expanded because
this is a fundamental fundamental issue
and we wanted to offer readers a
sufficient appreciation of what was out
there
the final chapter off the language
itself is database access I'm somewhat
surprised that it's in the book well
many distributed systems somehow use the
database yeah but you yeah yeah
obviously right but somehow for me it
feels somewhat different I don't think
so I find it it's a important chapter
but on the other hand we don't go into
too much depth here's also proxy
patterns basically there are the four
key database access
from martin fowler's a parent's
benchpress application but interesting
me we start with another pattern that is
not described in Martin's book which is
database access layer that goes back to
work from yin scold awry and Wolfgang
Keller who also and also from Kyle Brown
and redneck and they started off their
database patterns so accessing a
rational or object relational database
from an object-oriented system by
introducing a database access layer
Martin didn't address this but but we
thought where all these raw data gateway
stable data gateways active records
would live let's get it through the
system
um collected in a single place and that
is why we introduced database access
layer and moved on from there but it's
basically a chapter into into the many
patterns on object relational mapping oh
wow so but we find it important but if
you look at patterns that we have like
shared repository and blackboard so
there are some matters implemented with
database yes yes so we need a connection
right to reinforce that you can actually
see database access layer follows from
layers it follows from shared repository
and to go back to why we're surprised
why weren't you surprised when we
included patterns that dealt with views
you know many applications have some
user interface exactly yeah and the
point is that if we're going to deal
with views which maybe people see at the
top side of a system we are also going
to deal with the bottom side to be
little bit at the at the outside a
database is a different kind of
presentation layer is where it is in the
sense of it is it represents a form of
interaction and i/o it represents a
world of its own and so our point was
without this the language cannot be
fully considered complete but it's not
going to we're not going to give it the
same emphasis as perhaps resource
management which if we did in the
previous chapter ok since we are also
running out of time and also the book is
more or less we went through it let's
wrap up this episode the last chapter is
called a departing thought which is a
good like headline for this maybe
your last words on this episode on this
podcast here yeah well the departing
thought in the proposal for is basically
read pose-off I've proposed a 5 it's
just a transition towards Falls are 5
those are for doesn't include the
typical closure that other positive
volumes have like past present and
future earnings because those are 5 does
this it includes that chapters own
because they are
they were written more or less
simultaneously and never we published
more or less simultaneously those are
for has a very short ending saying okay
this is it and see you at pose a 5 and
yeah have fun developing you stupid
systems that is basically what is saying
yeah yeah cool so thank you both for
being on the podcast thank you very much
for interviewing us thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at se - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details